You know what it is, don't worry about it.
Hello and welcome to another episode of no such thing as a fish, a weekly podcast coming
to you from the QI offices in Hobern.
My name is Dan Schreiber, I am sitting here with Andrew Hunter Murray, Anna Toshinsky and
James Harkin.
And once again, we have gathered around the microphones with our four favorite facts
from the last seven days, and in no particular order, here we go.
Starting with fact number one, that is Andy.
My fact is, in 1886 there was a national craze for pushing a wheelbarrow the entire length
of Britain.
Fun.
Do you have TV?
No TV.
A problem that can be resolved by TV.
Craze is a big word, that means a lot, a lot of people would have had the rise of
jammed.
The main guy was called Bob Carlisle.
He did this in 1879.
He pushed a wheelbarrow from Landsend, which for international as the very, very far southwest
corner of the UK, to John O'Grotes, which is the very, very furthest north-east corner
of the UK.
And obviously the furthest tip of Scotland, it's what, a thousand miles as a pro flies,
it's six hundred and three miles.
Yeah.
So you wiggle around a bit and depending on your route, it will come to maybe six hundred
or fifty-seven hundred miles.
So he did this and it was kind of funny and it was a good stunt it got in the papers.
He did exploits and sort of fun stunts all the way through his life.
And then several years later there was a bit of a resurgence in popularity and lots of people
started doing it again as stunts.
And really between the lines it seems to have been a bit of a, not a charity thing, but
if you were broke and you wanted to raise lots of money for yourself, you know, this was
the thing you could do.
I mean, it's grueling to do.
Yeah.
So he just lost his job, this Carl Isle guy, right?
He lost his job for walking a tiger without a leash.
Right.
Okay.
And they said, right, you're not coming back to Woolworth's after that.
No, he worked in a circus.
I think it was without a muzzle as opposed to a lead.
Yes.
Sorry.
And he got kicked out of the circus and he thought, well, I don't have any money, but
I've heard that in America, a lot of people are walking around, so maybe I'll copy
what they're doing over here and become famous.
Yeah.
Okay.
And add a wheelbarrow.
Well, there was also a couple of Americans who'd walked from the east coast to the west coast
of America with wheelbarrow, so we probably took the idea from them.
He was inspired by them.
Yeah.
He was, I mean, he had an amazing career, didn't he?
He was a clown.
He worked in the circus.
He was a sailor.
He was overseas a lot.
And he was a real promoter.
He used to, when he was in the circus, go to towns ahead of them arriving and he would
build up the enthusiasm, the ticket sales, posters, PR, and that's exactly what he did with
this.
He would make sure that when he was in a town and taking rest, that he would write all the
papers saying, this amazing guy is coming to your town next.
Be ready.
Have everyone out to meet him and he would then arrive in the town and give improvised speeches
on the steps of the town hall, but not about the walk, just about I was a clown who walked
animals.
I was overseas.
I think he was talking about temperance a lot.
Yeah.
That was a big thing for him.
A big temperance guy.
And then was it him who sort of renaged on that?
Didn't he say that he was going to do the whole walk being T-Total and then at the end when
he was interviewed?
He said, do you know what?
Actually, I realised it was better for me to have a little bit to drink on root to make
it.
Yeah, basically.
He basically said at the styles, like everyone shouldn't drink alcohol and then by
the end he went, you know what?
Some people should drink alcohol, like people who have walked eight hundred miles.
This guy to probably do with a pint.
Absolutely fair enough.
Yeah.
It's a bit tragic because he did this.
He got some attention and a little bit of money, I think, but not a huge amount.
And then when the whole craze kicked off seven years later, he was in China.
He missed it.
Yeah.
He was looking for new types of wheelbarrow.
I think he was.
Because that's a niche callback, isn't it?
Oh my god.
Wonderful.
I think that's like episode two.
Callback, basically.
What's it to again?
It's a fact that I read a Paul Theroux book, which is he was talking to someone in China and
they said all the things they invented, paper, you know, dynamite, all this stuff, fireworks,
wheelbarrows.
And then he leans into Paul Theroux and says, we've even got wheelbarrows here in the east
that you guys don't even know about.
So he wasn't the first person to walk from John the Grotesque to Lansendor or vice versa,
right?
He was the first to do it with a wheelbarrow, I think.
But there was a pair of brothers called Robert and John Naylor, who first did it in 1871.
And they wrote a book about it.
And so that became quite famous.
The book was called, I don't know what the book was called.
I've got it.
It was called from John the Grotesque to Lansendor.
Oh, okay.
Yeah.
Right.
But what they did, we've said it's about 800 miles, but they walked 1,372 miles because they
just kept going on little details if there's something nice around the corner.
God, that would be so annoying.
Was there one of them who was always saying, oh, go and look at this, because I hate don't
you hate being on a walk with that person?
No, I am that person.
Yeah, absolutely.
I mean, too, I think I can see an information board over there.
Let's just pop over and read it.
Yeah, people were doing it all over the shop after that, weren't they?
It was very popular and people did variations of it, lots of dogs did it, people with their
own, as it wasn't like a separate dog contest.
There was a woman called Rosa Simmons.
Did you guys read about her?
No, no.
Again, it's pre-TV and pre-women having jobs days, so she, between 1902 and 1907, she did it
seven times, but she didn't do the John the Grotesque to Lansend, she did, because she lived
in London, so she had to get to the start point and the end point, so she did London to John
the Grotesque to Lansend to London seven times.
Oh, my God.
Two of the years, she did it twice every summer.
So you know, she did 25 days on the hook of doing that whole thing and then thought I'll do it
again.
And she said that it really kind of cured her, that unvegetarianism, of being very sickly.
Oh, okay.
You haven't mentioned this.
She was sick.
Just a casual cure.
Yeah.
I was reading about John the Grotes.
It seems to have been named after a 15th century Dutchman called Jan de Groot or John
of Groot, and he used to apply a ferry between the Scottish mainland and Orkney, so he supposedly
had a house there, which has, since been knocked down, there's a hotel sitting on it today.
And it was him and seven other members of his family who had all their families there.
And they used to have a dispute when they got together for big meals who sat at the head
of the table.
So what they ended up building is an octagon building with eight doors.
Well, I've landed MMA fights to decide who exactly they had eight doors to the house.
Because I think what didn't they also have fights about who had precedence when you
entered the house before even sitting at the table?
Exactly.
It was just, it was a whole thing about, I'm the major person in this family.
I think this family's got problems that are beyond the structural.
Are you sure?
And because I thought at the start of the sentence, you were going to say, "I see a format."
Okay.
Now we're talking.
And so what would happen is they would open the eight doors.
The heads would walk in, and there would be eight tables that were positioned facing each
other, each of which had a head at the top.
And so they could each sit at like an asterisk, like an asterisk.
Exactly.
Wait.
It's not just eight people coming in.
No, no.
And their family's.
Oh, okay.
Yes.
I think eight doors is nuts.
I'm sorry.
Oh, I don't think I pitched that as a story of logic and why are we all doing that?
I don't agree.
That was nuts.
But yeah, John not brought it.
It was very rundown, John Agrotes, for a long time.
I think it's a fair bit nicer now.
Nice.
It's the most dismal place in Scotland by a magazine, it's got a magazine called Urban Realm.
You had to pay a tenor to have your photo taken with the sign.
Yeah, there's a famous sign saying this far to London, this far to London.
Tenor.
Yeah, and those days as well, in Scotland as well.
Yeah.
That was until 2013.
I think there is now a free sign that you can have your picture taken out.
But yeah, that was because you know, I guess the bloke had to go and get the sign out of
the shed or whatever.
No.
It's just tough.
It's tough times.
Put it in the ground, mate.
It says like, landsend 874 miles or something, because that's, if you go by road, that's how long
it takes.
I think that's what it says.
But that is the old version that it was 874 miles and now it's 814 miles, so it's actually
60 miles shorter distance than it was when people were doing it 100 and a half years ago.
Right.
Are we riddling me this?
It can do.
Okay.
Coastal erosion.
Oh.
Yes.
Each coast has been eroded by 30 miles, and that part of the country has disappeared.
Final hours of look at it in Chris.
Chris.
Until last time you watched it, it's been a million years.
It's been gone for like a decade.
Well, it's got to be just highways tunnels kind of thing.
It's bridges.
The Seven Bridge is a big one, because actually if you go from landsend to Jonah Groats, you
go through Wales for a little bit of it.
So you go off the Seven Bridge and then you're in Wales for a tiny bit and then you go
up the west coast of England.
But yeah, the Seven Bridge, there's a few other bridges, the Kesset Bridge, Chromacy Bridge,
the Donut Firth Bridge.
They've all shot in the route that you have to take, whereas you used to have to go round
these rivers.
Oh, to the round river, isn't it?
Yeah.
You just have to wait until there's a Ford that you can get over.
The Ford.
Yeah.
Okay.
That's amazing that our country's got smaller on the inside due to infrastructure.
I think that's really cool.
Yeah.
It's more than by some measures.
I think that it's not actually the most northerly point and nor is landsend the most
south-westernly point.
So not none of it's true.
Is it?
It's all rubbish.
It's actually nearby Dunnett Head, near Jonah Groats, which is the most northerly point,
but I think it's just a bit less accessible.
I think the guy who had that sign charged £12 a picture.
And the longest journey possible in the UK isn't even that route.
It's landsend to Duncan's Behead because that's another Basin Scotland, which is further
away.
And also, what's great Britain's westernmost point?
Well, you want us to say something Cornish because it feels like it's big.
I do want you to say something Cornish.
But it's probably that we're at an angle, so it's somewhere in Scotland.
Yeah.
It's in Scotland.
I'll add an American point on the west coast of Scotland, which is when you look at almost
any map of Britain, obviously Cornwall sticks project massively, but again, our maps
are screwed, aren't they?
Britain's doing a wheelie, basically.
Yes.
Yeah.
Right.
Which is how they did the wheelbarrow as well.
Yeah.
This is one, which of these has taken less time.
OK.
The record for the penny-farthing journey.
So that's on a giant wheel.
It's like a weird looking bicycle, old school.
Yeah.
Penny-farthing?
Or some people might not know it.
For overseas listeners, we actually, we all compute some of those.
You can get an app and just hire a penny-farthing.
Yeah.
So penny-farthing.
The fastest shed record, or skipping with a skipping rope.
The fastest shed record, going with it carrying a shed?
No, that would be a motorised with wheels, I'm guessing, because we've done speed records
for shed before.
For overseas listeners, those of us who can't afford to get a penny-farthing app, we
actually get a shed app.
There's a few people getting those, but that's why it's a bit cheaper.
And you drill holes in the bottom, you put your legs through, and then everyone just
runs.
Like the fun stuff, yeah.
What was the third one?
The shed.
Skipping rope.
As in...
Yeah.
We need to explain.
For those of us who haven't been...
For those of us who haven't been.
The car with planks on it.
And if it's a good out of bolts of rubber.
No, it's just so amazing.
Every fact we have you find a wavelength to one of your rotation
of ten favourite people.
Anyway, it's called Musical Bumps.
And he says...
We're not going to explain for international listeners
who the quite long dead comedian Dudley Moore is.
That's fine.
That's a very good point.
Yeah, he was in Arthur.
He was in the movie Tenwood Bo Derek.
He was in Beyond the Fringe, which was a landmark moment
in that time, within this country.
Yeah, okay.
Sure.
Yeah, yeah.
I was having fun.
He says that a lot of great piano players
don't have white and black keys.
They have yellow and black.
And it's because the heaviness of which they play
and slam their keys, discolors it.
And so the white keys go yellow.
Is it swat or do they all smoke or...?
I think it has to just be a mixture of what they've eaten,
what they've like.
It's just, it's wear and tear-based.
It really?
What's it?
It's done.
But yeah, he said it to the point where anytime he saw
the color yellow, he associated it with loudness
because it was usually on a piano player who would slam
the keys that you would see yellow.
And when he died at his funeral, he had a bouquet
that was made into a big piano and it was black and yellow.
And I think that was in reference to...
Oh, really?
Yeah.
Most remote piano in the world?
Antarctica.
Mars.
Oh, in the world.
No answer.
I refuse to play your silly questions anymore.
Oh.
Yeah.
Gosh, I remember they did take one so one time to cut.
They did.
That's why I said that.
Antarctica.
That's correct.
That's a player piano, right, I think.
It was...
No, I think it was just a standard upright.
Okay.
But Captain Scott took one to the Antarctic.
Did he?
Yeah.
And this is the very sidetrack where they all died.
But this is not the fault of the piano,
which they did not take all the way to the South Pole.
They left it at their base.
Okay.
Which was sensible.
And it was...
Some of them were still questioning whether they should have brought it in the first place.
But the really interesting why they brought it in the first place,
which was just that music was so important for morale.
Moral, yeah.
And when you're there in the dark, polar night and it's just...
It's so bloody cold and you can't go outside and you need morale.
And so one of them said we should have gone mad in the long wind tonight
if they hadn't had the piano with them.
So it was used a lot.
They would all stand around singing.
And they practically had a full choir going around it.
They would sing a lot together in the evenings.
And it's still there to this day.
Is it?
Yeah.
Playable as anyone in a concert.
I think a tuner would probably manage to improve it a little bit.
Yeah.
The white and black notes are made of ivory.
Ebony and ivory.
But you can't sell ivory anymore.
So they don't make them.
Because of work.
Because of dead elephants.
Yes.
Or woke, whichever way you want to put it.
That's what I call it, yeah.
But also, did you know Ebony is also endangered?
Of the woods.
Yeah, the Ebony would.
So it grows really, really slowly.
It takes about 200 years to get dense enough that you can turn it into piano keys.
And so to save the trees, there's real strict controls on the Ebony trade.
Wow.
And also, the Ebony trees, the fruit is eaten by elephants who poo out the fruits to get more trees.
So actually, Ebony and ivory come together in perfect harmony.
Oh, wow.
So they all grow.
It's incredible.
Okay, it is time for fact number three, and that is Anna.
My fact this week is that until the mid-19th century,
the official language of Hungary was Latin.
And this is amazing.
This was just much longer than any other country continued to use Latin.
So a lot of other European countries used it as a sort of legal
and sometimes administrative language until the Reformation, Enlightenment period.
But Hungary just kept it on.
And it continued to be used, first of all, in official circumstances,
like the law, state administration, and things like that.
But also, everyday chat and foreign travelers would go at the start of the 19th century to Hungary
and say, "This is absolute desire.
I just went into a pub."
And the innkeeper was chatting and laughing to me.
It's crazy.
Imagine that today.
It's almost like going to one of these old times places.
We talked about that big French.
You know, that's sort of your back in time.
Yeah.
Hungary was one big Puy de Fu.
So bizarre.
There was a record written actually by Cassanova of sex fame.
Who did write about all of these?
He would be delighted with that.
Super clay.
So do you mean Cassanova the librarian?
He met a Hungarian traveler at one point who said he'd been incredibly disappointed
when he visited Rome because naturally he thought it was Hungarian
who was speaking Latin every day to his kids.
He thought he'd go to Rome and obviously they'd all be speaking in decent society.
And he said, "I was greatly mistaken.
Nobody can speak it, not even the priests who only pretend to write it."
That's so funny.
Is it because Hungary is so hard to learn?
There's various reasons, I think.
I mean, it was a ruler called Maria Tureza who sort of stamped this in stone in the 1700s
when people were thinking, "Shall we give up this old dead language thing?"
Yeah, she was a Habsburg, right?
Yeah.
And then there was the War of Austrian Succession where someone had died.
She was in charge.
And all the other princes around Europe, because the Habsburg Empire was absolutely huge.
All these princes decided, "Oh, well, we've got a chance here.
We can sell our own countries."
And so she decided to fight them and sort of knock them all down.
And when she won that war, she decided to kind of bring a new enlightened state
and get rid of Latin from all these countries.
But in Hungary, she couldn't really do it because it was so diverse.
The aristocrats spoke French, the gentry spoke magia.
The peasants were kind of Germanic.
So everyone spoke different languages.
But if we keep it in Latin, then everyone could kind of stick together.
Right.
Yeah.
She had a lot of kids, by the way.
Very interesting lady.
She had, I believe it was 16 kids.
And the 15th kid during labor.
She had a tooth taken out while she was having her 15th kid.
Because she hated time wasting and she thought,
"Okay, if I'm going to be in pain anyway, let's do this at the same time."
That's a really good idea.
Really?
Yeah.
Yeah, do those things in the lead up to birth during labor while you're in agony as it is?
Seems like an interesting thought.
I think that's a good new business for a dentist, isn't it?
You're in labor.
Just turn up the guy.
Would you like me to do any fib?
Well, this is going on.
Exactly.
But she gave birth and she gave birth to a daughter called Antonia.
And Antonia went on to become Marie Antoinette.
Yes.
Oh, Piotwist.
Yeah, Piotwist.
Piotwist, yeah.
She also had 52.
I think it was 52 grandchildren.
Wow.
56.
A lot of grandchildren.
I mean, that's a hell of a lot of grandchildren.
Because her kids, a couple of her kids went on to have 16 or 17 or 18 kids.
And if all the parents want you to do one day a week, with one of the grandchildren, that's a nightmare.
One more thing is that the Habsburg realm had a lot of Latin going on, which means that actually
Croatia also had Latin as its main language until 1847.
Yes.
Again, because it was an old Habsburg realm.
And it was part of the Hungarian Empire at this time, which is one of the reasons they didn't go Hungarian.
Because they didn't speak Hungarian.
Another thing about Maria Teresa, she couldn't be crowned properly crowned because she was a woman
and that was against the Hungarian rules at the start.
But then she did impress the nobles by, you know, trampling all over them in her first year.
So then they did say, all right, we can do it.
We will crown you.
Empress, queen.
No, not queen.
Because they didn't have a concept of it.
King?
So she was crowned king.
Yes.
She was king Maria Teresa.
Go boss, absolutely go boss.
Rex Hungarian.
Yeah.
Very cool.
And just couldn't come up with the feminine.
Do you think Latin is going to come back?
Yeah.
There's a group called Via Nova who wants to revive Latin in Europe.
Like in the EU, for instance, at the moment everyone kind of speaks English or French.
All their own languages.
But they think maybe if we bring Latin back, then there'll be no like cultural baggage that comes with saying,
we have to do this bit in Serbo Croats and we have to do this bit in Italian and we have to do this bit.
How many people are asking for this?
Well, there's a small group.
Anyway, there's a linguistic scholar called Jennifer Jenkins, who says,
"As far as I understand it, the EU doesn't have any problem using English at the moment,
especially now that Britain isn't there anymore."
Oh, thank you Jennifer.
And also, there is no way that the Chinese are going to learn Latin.
That's a fair point.
Which I think is a good point.
Hey, I've got a quiz for you guys.
What do you think this term means in Hungary?
His mouth is walking like the ass of a duck.
Oh.
So an ass of a duck is wobbling like, so maybe you're going, "Bul-ul-ul-ul-ul-ul."
Did they do that?
I'm not an hungry to have a French word.
Yeah.
He's just talking Bullocks.
He talks a lot, is basically.
Oh, of course.
This is what they say for someone he's talking about.
Here's another one.
"Why are you giving drinks to the mice?"
That's just literal.
If someone gives drinks to mice, that's the perfect, we know what we'll think to say.
Because it's ridiculous things to do.
Well, is it a waste?
You're wasting them.
They won't enjoy them.
It's why are you crying?
Why are you giving drinks to the mice?
Presumably, the film Terminator 2, I think includes that line.
Where Arnold Schwarzenegger says, "Why do you cry to a little boy?"
Yeah.
So when they translate it, it's hilarious.
I presume he said, "Why do you give drinks to the mice?"
Oh, we've got to watch that version, though.
Your dad was not a glassmaker.
Oh.
So glassmakers, they're working hot conditions, don't they?
In Venice?
He was clumsy.
He's really clumsy.
Your dad's really clumsy.
You're blocking my view.
Hey, your dad is not a glassmaker.
You are not.
You make a better dog than a window.
Yes.
That's the proper way of saying it.
Yeah, and the last one, the fence is not made of sausage.
The fence is not made of sausage.
So stop chewing on it.
So pigs make sausages and they need fences to keep them in.
Oh.
So you wouldn't make the fence out of the stuff that the pigs are going to be turned into?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So it's like post-to game-keeper stuff.
No, it's not as good as you think.
It's what they would say for if they were saying it's not as good as you think.
The fence is not made of sausage.
I mean, it would be good, wouldn't it?
Yeah.
Exactly.
I can see that it's your fantasy, Andy.
For a farmer, I don't know.
The main thing about Hungarian, aside from these bizarre phrases that they have,
when they did decide to go with Hungarian as the official language,
it was quite out of date they decided.
And it couldn't have words with things like, you know,
like, lathe or something like the 19th century.
A plow.
Train?
A motor car.
A train.
I don't know.
And the lathe, I would have said they probably had those for that century.
No, I mean, they had a piano.
Oh, good.
Well, they were invented a century ago, so I'm going to probably go to them.
Can we just have a give or take here?
So they had lots of stuff they didn't have words for.
Okay.
Charles Dickens, they didn't have a word for Charles Dickens.
The telegraph.
Very good.
So they had to invent some new words.
A guy called Ferenc Kaczynski was the leader of this in academic.
This is a lot like what I talked it in Turkey, right,
when he was redoing Turkish.
But guess how many words they invented?
And if I tell you that in ordinary day-to-day language,
the number of words that you probably know from your native language
is between 15,000 and 20,000.
And that's word family.
So run, running, runs.
That would all be one word.
Okay.
So how many new words were created for the Hungarian language?
Thousands.
Yeah.
With family words, as well.
I think it is, yeah.
Okay.
Well, this is the claim I haven't heard.
And this is said in all, like books about it, histories of Hungary.
So you're going to read a lot of a few.
I think James has shot himself at the foot with guessing 1,000,
because that's quite a reasonable guess.
I would say--
The way that this works is the first person to say something
gives a reasonable guess.
Yeah.
Then the next two you spoil the game.
That's how this always works.
And it's not fun for anyone.
Six.
Love that.
Thank you, Andy, and what do you want a billion?
Two billion.
Yeah.
Andy's closest.
Oh.
It was 10,000 words.
Okay.
Sorry, why did they--
Okay, that's two thirds of the total number of words
that you would know in a native language.
This is the language everyone's been speaking for thousands of years.
And some bloke comes along and says,
I've added 10,000 words.
Here's your folk, Iblist.
Memorize it by next week.
Yeah, that's a lot.
Unbelievable.
I know one word in Hungarian.
Ega Shigerdra, which means cheers.
Oh, which tells you a lot what I did when I was in Hungary.
[LAUGHTER]
But do you know how-- we talked about space earlier.
Do you know how there's this idea of, like,
if there are aliens, where are they?
The Thurby paradox.
Well, Leo Slizard, who was a physicist,
said that the answers to the Thurby paradox
is that the aliens are among us,
but they call themselves Hungarians.
Yes.
And this is kind of a group of really genius Hungarians
that came across at the start of the 20th century,
that were just, like, transforming all of science and everything.
And they were known as the Martians,
because they were just, like, so far ahead
of everyone else in the world.
Really?
Interesting, yes.
That was about-- maybe it was because they learned Latin for so long.
Well, Hungary was a very big country,
like a very big and important country for so long,
and then they lost a lot of--
they kind of slightly got on the wrong side during the war.
[LAUGHTER]
And then when the war finished, they lost all of their land.
Which war first war?
Both, actually.
Because as we've ascertained recently,
there was no wrong side to be over the first world war.
Exactly.
What I mean by the wrong side is the losing side.
Ah, so the GDP would have been the same as Britain,
if not more.
And then suddenly, just all went wrong.
I think in 1946, after World War II,
if you went to a restaurant in Hungary,
which for a few people could do,
but if you went to restaurant in Hungary,
it was better to order your meal and then pay for it at the start of a meal,
because, by the end of the meal, inflation was so high,
it would have gone up.
I think they were really--
Yeah, it was massive.
The currency was like the pengo or something, wasn't it?
Yes.
And you could like get five billion pengo notes.
Yeah.
It was like, basically, when you went to pay for a meal,
it was like they were spoiling one of our guessing games.
Right.
How much is this burger?
Oh, is it two billion pengo's?
Yes, it is.
I can't believe we're sitting in the fact
where we literally could have had the quiz question over that.
OK, it is time for a final fact of the show.
And that is James.
OK, my fact this week is that Stephen King's wife threatened to divorce him
for playing mumbo number five so often.
Bump, bump, bump, bump, bump.
How often do we know how often?
I want to see it enough.
I think that's right.
No judge would you be granted all the assets.
So this was an interview that the horror author Stephen King did with Rolling Stone.
And he said, my wife threatened to divorce me.
I played that a lot.
I had the dance mix.
I love those extended play things.
And I played both sides of it.
And one of them was just a total instrumental.
And I played that finger till my wife just said one more time
and I'm going to have to fucking leave you.
Wow.
So it's just seen that he really liked it.
And I don't think, I don't know because this is all the information I have in it.
But I don't think it's the Lou Baker version.
Because this is quite an old mumbo song, right?
Oh, not that old, but it's a mid 20th century mumbo song.
Well, Stephen King listening after the Lou Baker version was...
He was working on a book.
He thinks he was working on a book called 112263,
which was a time travel novel in which someone goes back to try
and prevent the assassination of JFK.
Absolute Baker.
Yeah.
So who knows, you could be right James.
It could be a dance mix.
Surely.
No, because if he was listening to the words and then the instrumental,
maybe he was doing Lou Baker and then...
Yeah, maybe.
I see what you mean by that.
But I went on Spotify and looked for all the different versions of mumbo.
Number five, I could find.
And most of the instrumental versions would not be the Lou Baker version.
That's interesting.
So correct your phone wrong.
This was an old mumbo song by a guy called Perez.
Perez Perez Prado.
Perez Prado.
But that didn't have words?
No, it's just like the background mumbo song.
Yes.
The version I know and love is the one with a little bit of bit of it.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Okay, okay, okay.
So he sounds like he was listening to both versions, maybe.
I think he must have been listening to both.
If it was just a word version, then that can only be...
I do see that, yeah.
It's Stephen King, he's low brow, let's face it.
He's gone Lou Baker.
No offense.
Would you like me to hold your coat?
I think that's right, I think.
And, you know, I don't know if you guys have done it, I certainly do.
If I'm writing something when I wrote my books and Andy, when you write your books,
you don't want lyrics and you want something on repeat going over and over.
And there might be a horrible song, but if it's chosen you, as it were,
to help your creativity.
I listen to J-pop because I can't understand the words, right?
I wouldn't listen to anything on repeat.
Interesting.
I wrote my school's dissertation to the core is live version of only when I sleep over and over.
I think I did it like a thousand times.
That's insane.
And that has lyrics, but I think once it's just going, you forget.
It's interesting.
So yeah, let's get into Mambo number four.
Yeah, and we also, let's just say when Dan says, if it's a terrible song,
this is not a terrible song.
This is a brilliant song.
It's definitely one of my favourite Mambo's.
This is my five top Mambo's, yeah.
So Lou Beger, named after his own surname, because he's called David Lou Beger.
I think middle name maybe.
David Lou Beger, Balamesi?
Yeah, David Lou Beger is what he goes by now.
So he's recently written an autobiography called Mambo number one,
which is under his name David Lou Beger.
Who is reading how many copies of that autobiography being so well once a Monica, once a return?
And yeah, he was, I think he was German, wasn't he?
He is German.
Yeah.
Or in West Germany.
I don't think of Lou Beger and the Cold War in the same space.
But one of the first times this was ever played was very, very sadly.
His father died a few weeks before the song came out.
But Lou Beger visited him in hospital with an early version of the song.
And I think this was on his father's deathbed, was he played him?
Mambo number five.
Fantastic.
His father apparently said this will open doors and kind of gave his blessing to the song
and said you've done a great, great thing there.
Because I think he hadn't had a huge commercial success before that.
This was definitely his biggest hit, you know.
But I just find the idea of having to go into the bedside and then put on the desk.
That is, it's not what we did expect. I wonder if he got confused at the line
a little bit of Sandra in the sun, because Lou Beger's sister is called Sandra.
No, that's not so.
Oh, might have sounded a bit odd to the dad on his deathbed.
There were so many other women's names with two syllables.
Oh, they were.
How were you?
They were short of that.
You will never think of another one.
Oh, wow.
Yeah.
I was trying to see if there was anything deeper to the fact that Stephen King really latched on to this song.
So, number five was the debut song for Lou Beger.
Yeah.
Back in 1974, Carrie was the debut for Stephen King.
And so I had a look through Carrie.
And remarkably, in the song, you've got Monica Erika Rita, Tina Sandra, Mary and Jessica.
Rita, Tina Sandra, Mary and Jessica are all characters in Carrie.
And then Erika appears in Carrie the movie.
And then Monica in the sequel to the Carrie movie, which came out many years later.
So, all of them appear as part of...
Do you think Mary Lou Beger was reading Carrie when he was writing this?
It's possible.
I mean, I think it goes deeper as well, because Stephen King.
Let's go through all the ways of the talk I think, Dad.
Stephen King released Carrie in 1974 as a hardback.
Sold modestly, but didn't do as well to make him who he is today.
It was 1975, when the paperback came out, exploded.
Sold millions.
That's why Stephen King is who he is today.
That was released in April 1975.
The same month and year that Lou Beger was born.
So, something is cooking.
Something is cooking underneath them.
I mean, if Stephen King isn't turning this into a tedious novel, right?
No, that's very novel.
How dare you.
Here's another slightly interesting thing.
It's lovely.
It does.
Don't over sell it.
Manbo.
What does Manbo mean?
It's a female priestess in the...
What do they do in Haiti?
Yeah, voodoo.
Yeah, voodoo religion.
That's one.
I think it was named after a thing that meant kind of conversation, chat, chat, chat, in sort of Swahili.
Although, I always thought of it as meaning kind of shacking.
Well, it is also a word that the Bantu languages use.
And it translates as king.
Stephen King.
Stephen Manbo.
How many languages did you have to go deep into?
Well, what's more interesting is that they were...
They were even more interesting.
They were of six major shona languages that use Manbo as the title king.
One of which, one of the language dialects, is Monica.
It's called Monica.
M-A-N-Y-I-K-A.
I would love to see your string cork border at home where you have been plotting this out.
I'm just shocked I'm not getting a standing ovation right now.
This is wild.
That's so good.
It's, I'm wild by the work.
It's just interesting.
Here is a fun mathematical thing about Manbo number five.
Okay.
I found a really nice essay by a radical Damie Pack, which is based on these names.
So we've got Angela Pamela Sandra Rita, Monica Erika Tina, Mary Jessica.
Here I am.
A little bit of you makes me a man.
Well, can you predict the song's date of release based on the names of the women?
Oh, I see, when were they most popular for children?
And then presumably they're in their 20s when he's dating them.
So is it Bayesian reasoning or the Bayes formula?
Yeah.
And it's you're measuring the distribution of the names and their popularity.
And you combine, you've got several different probabilities, right?
Because you've got all these different names.
So you can combine them and come up with a kind of, I'm sure I'm absolutely butchering this explanation.
But you know, some names like Jessica only really came in in the 60s and 70s.
Whereas if Pamela was popular a century before, it's probably not that one.
Because you're combining it with the Jessica.
And as the writer said, remember number five was released in 1999.
But the popular baby girl names of 1999 would not automatically tell us the song was released that year.
Lou Baker wasn't meeting newborn infants.
That was most flirting with adult women.
So we need to look at the probability of names from the 60s and 70s and 80s.
I'm sure he's relieved we've clarified that.
And lo and behold, this formula comes up with 1999 as the date of release.
Is that right?
When you combine the names and you do the reasoning.
Because they knew what answer they were aiming for, didn't they?
I'm not mathematically qualified enough to say.
James, are you saying the kind of academics who would write a paper like this might be not being the most rigorous they possibly could be statistically?
I'm absolutely not getting on the amateur shitski.
Let's attack on that.
And then expand like it.
I've forgotten that.
I thought you were going to say it.
Here's a mathematical thing about manbo number five.
Isn't it weird that there's a soul manbo number five.
And then that same original artist wrote a soul manbo number eight.
But there aren't any others.
Well, I think they were.
I couldn't find any.
I couldn't find number number seven, but by a different artist.
But I couldn't find one to four.
This is Perez Prado that we're talking about who was the original writer of manbo number five.
But he wrote so many songs with the name Manbo in it.
He didn't necessarily record all of them.
So it's quite possible that he had live versions.
Manbo one, two, three, four, five made it big.
Yeah, Luke Perez Prado, I had, I as a child had one of his records in my record collection because he did the theme for a Guinness advert.
Where there's like a guy dancing around a pint of Guinness.
And that song became absolutely massive.
But he also wrote quite a few other songs that you'd recognize.
So one of them is called Patricia, which is the first number one track in America that has an organ as a lead instrument.
And it's in that loads of Tarantino movies, so you would definitely know it.
And he originally did cha cha cha music, but then went on to Manbo.
And then went on to loads of other stuff.
So he wrote a four movement tone poem that combined jazz and Afro Cuban themes.
And then in 1967 Che Guevara died.
And in Cuba, they announced the, they did the newscast.
But at the start of the newscast, they played one of his songs, which was called the exotic suite of the Americas.
And then whenever they had any commemoration of Che Guevara's death, they always played.
I almost said a Lou Baker song.
But Perez Prado's song.
Really?
How much?
A little bit of Che in Bolivia.
There's no lyrics in his original member number five.
But he did do a lot of different manboes, number number eight and so on.
But apparently there's a really good way.
Let's say you're sitting in a cafe and you hear what sounds like a Perez Prado song coming on over the speakers.
How do you tell that it's him and not just a random manbo song?
There is apparently a little way, a little trick.
Ooh.
Sort of an audio signature.
Yeah, exactly.
And you did it earlier when you were saying the lyrics to the song.
When Andi won.
In all his songs, there's just a little.
Wait, but no, but Lou Baker does that.
Or does he?
I probably Lou Baker does do that.
We're back to the full board.
Lou Baker probably does do that.
But he's doing it in tribute to Prado.
Because that's what Prado did all the way in every song.
No, but it definitely is him who does it.
It's not a ghost of Prado suddenly comes on over the speakers.
And it knows the song so well.
Yeah, he was known as Seal Face.
Perez Prado because of this thing that he did whenever he was playing.
And he was making a bit like a seal.
Yeah, I can see that.
It's good.
I think we should fold in some kind of audio signature like that.
To our show.
Yeah, okay.
And any suggestions?
Ooh.
Just a suggestion to get us off the blocks.
So everyone knows that it's us.
Yeah.
If you're just in a cafe and a random podcast comes on and you hear.
Ooh.
They're like, oh, I know this one.
It's a piece of cake.
You notice it.
Um, this is a manbo came from Danzone,
which is Cuba's national dance.
I'm sorry, the Danzone.
The Danzone.
Oh, God.
And we are just supposed to believe this means nothing.
Yeah.
Isn't that cool?
That was the worst part of the Crystal Maze, wasn't it?
When you went to the Danzone.
I'll go for another mystery game, fine.
No, no, no.
You're in the Danzone now.
And he's explaining to you about the time that Peter Sellers
met the old Barry Humphrey's.
I don't want the money.
I'm afraid Danzone is Cuba's national dance.
Danzone.
Um, and, uh, so that is what Manbo grew out of.
It was like building off that and I just added an improvised
section to the end.
But Danzone is very interesting because, um,
it's a dance and it's split into two sections.
Uh, the music, one section, one type of section you dance to,
the other you don't dance to.
And so there are these long sections of no dancing.
And the way to spot a novice who's in their first dance is
that they don't know when the non-dance sections come.
So there are subtle hints in the music, which mean stop dancing.
Can I just say what you're describing is musical statues?
So is it halfway through a Danzone?
Like everyone starts and if someone moves their out.
It's exactly that.
They invented the Cuban's invented musical statues.
Okay, that's it.
That is all of our facts.
Thank you so much for listening.
If you'd like to get in contact with any of us about the things
that we've said over the course of this podcast,
we can all be found online.
I'm on @Streiberland on Instagram.
Andy.
Hi, Andrew Hunter M. James.
No, so you're saying this James Harkin.
And, Anna, if they want to get us as a group.
You can go to Instagram at no such thing or email podcast at qi.com.
Yeah, podcast at qi.com.
That's the most important one of all because Andy receives
all your emails and he cherry picks the best to bring to two new shows
that we've been making over the last few months.
There is little fish, our bonus Monday show,
where we put down our facts and we just say your best facts
from the last seven days.
So send them in there or if you do have things that you want to say
about the stuff that we've mentioned, that all gets cherry picked
taken to our extra bonus hidden show, which is sitting in club fish
called Drop us a Line.
Now, club fish is on Patreon, Patreon.com/clubfish.
We have lots of rewards for different tiers.
You can get videos of some of the shows that we make.
There is extra long versions of the shows that you hear.
There's a bunch of stuff there.
Check it out.
Otherwise, just come back here next week because we're going to be back.
Thank you, as ever, to Lee and Lee, Ethan Ruperallia,
as well as the larger fish buster team for all their work.
We'll see you again next week.
Good bye.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
(upbeat music)
[BLANK_AUDIO]